( Suspenseful instrumental music )
( Dramatic instrumental music )
301A to car 5W , code one .
5W to 301A , go ahead , Johnny .
JOHNNY : We 're chasing wind , Ben .
Maybe the guy who sent in that report drank his breakfast . Let 's call it .
Wait a minute .
JOHNNY : It 's a kid , all right . Maybe 50 yards off the road .
I 'll keep circling her until you pick her up .
- 10-10 . - 10-10 .
( Dramatic instrumental music )
BEN : Hey !
Hey , honey !
BEN : Hey , little girl . Little girl !
Wait a minute . What are you doing out here ?
Honey
what 's your name ?
Who do you belong to ?
JOHNNY : Car 5W , code one .
Car 5W to 301A , go ahead .
( Radio crackle and interference )
10-9 , Johnny .
JOHNNY : There 's a trailer three miles from you , off the road .
I didn 't see anybody around it , you better check it out . 10-10 .
Okay , Johnny . 10-10 .
- What 's the matter with her ? - I don 't know .
ED : Sunstroke ?
BEN : She 's not sunburned . Couldn 't have been in the sun long .
Looks like she 's in shock .
Johnny spotted a car and trailer up ahead . Maybe she 's from there .
BEN : Maybe so .
( Suspenseful instrumental music )
ED : No use waking her up unless somebody can identify her . I 'll check it .
- BEN : What is it ? - ED : Have a look .
This blood must be 10 or 12 hours old .
Whatever happened here was either last night or early this morning .
Check outside .
( Dramatic instrumental music )
ED : It was sure no traffic accident , was it ?
This wasn 't caved in . It was caved out .
Did you find anything ?
No footprints or tire marks .
Found this .
I picked up just one . Six or seven more are scattered over there .
- Sugar . - Yeah .
There 's something over here you should look at .
I don 't know if it 's important , but see what you think .
Mountain lions never come down to the desert .
BEN : No cat ever lived would leave a print like that .
ED : Maybe something was set down there .
A bag , or a can , something like that .
It could be almost anything .
I found these inside .
Put in a call for fingerprint and moulage equipment , right away .
ED : Right .
- BEN : Have the medics pick up the kid . - ED : Right .
Car 5W to KMA-628 . Come in , please .
RADIO OPERATOR : KMA-628 to car 5W , go ahead .
We 're 12 miles north of the crossroads .
Halfway up the secondary road to White Butte .
Station wagon and house trailer with Illinois license plates .
They look pretty well beat up . Looks like a 9-14 .
Picked up a little girl who seems to be in shock .
Send ambulance and medics . We 'll stay here till you arrive .
Anything else ?
ED : Ben ?
10-10 .
RADIO OPERATOR : KMA-628 to 5W , location previously reported by 301 - A
will dispatch ambulance .
BEN : Hi , Reggie , how are the kids ?
- REGGIE : Fine . Another one on the way . - BEN : Good for you .
- MEDIC : Know what happened to her ? - BEN : No .
- MEDIC : Don 't know her name ? - BEN : No .
BEN : Take good care of her .
Give her a nice , easy ride . I 'll be with her all the way to the hospital .
( High-pitched stridulation )
( Stridulation fades )
MEDIC : What was that ?
I don 't know .
It must be the wind . It gets pretty freakish in these parts .
Yeah .
BEN : I 'll come soon . I want to be there when she starts talking .
( Wind whistles )
BEN : You know what that is , Cliff ?
I haven 't the faintest idea .
BEN : Hurry before the wind fills it in . Looks like a sandstorm is kicking up .
- You got any idea what happened ? - No .
Nothing that adds up .
How old you figure that kid is ?
Five or six .
Tough break for her .
They don 't need us right now .
Let 's go down to Gramps Johnson 's store and see what he knows .
( Wind howls )
BEN : Gramps ?
Gramps !
( Faint radio broadcast )
( Radio becomes louder )
Beats me .
Look , Ed , put in a call ...
Wait a minute .
BEN : Gramps .
Looks like he was dragged and thrown down there .
( Tense instrumental music )
- BEN : What do you make of it ? - ED : What did you make of the trailer ?
This wasn 't pushed in , it was pulled out . Just like at the trailer .
ED : Ben , have a look at this .
Sugar .
Money wasn 't taken here either .
This is another 9-14 . I 'll call for the guys at the trailer to come .
I want to be at headquarters when the girl talks .
ED : I 'll stick around and ride with them .
- Okay . Stay loose . - Sure .
( Switches off radio )
( High-pitched stridulation )
( High-pitched stridulation becomes louder )
( Gunshots )
( Ed screaming )
( High-pitched stridulation continues )
CAPTAIN : With all this , we only know the car and trailer was owned by
a man named Alan Elinson from Chicago .
Yeah , that 's all .
Stop blaming yourself for what happened to Ed Blackburn . It wasn 't your fault .
Somebody had to stay at Johnson 's place , so it happened to be Ed .
Yeah , I know .
We 'll find out who killed him , if he 's dead , along with Gramps and the Elinson family .
So come off it .
We 'll get a report on the fingerprints some time this morning . It 'll tell us more .
- Have you figured out what this print is ? - No .
Great .
CAPTAIN : Kit , run down all Gramps ' personal stuff and records .
I don 't think he had an enemy in the world , but somebody might have ...
No , wait , that doesn 't make sense .
If somebody wanted to knock off Gramps why tear down half the building to do it ?
I put in a call to check out all the mental institutions .
Everything seems to indicate a homicidal maniac .
There 's no money stolen , violent wreckage . Just sugar taken .
That 's being checked , but it 's a waste of time , too .
We 'd have been notified if there was a loony killer on the loose .
Gramps got off four shots from his 30-30 before the killer did this to the gun .
And Blackburn was a crack shot . He could hit anything he could see .
Unless your maniac was armored like a battleship
there 's no maniac in this case .
Yeah , you 're right .
I want every available man scouting the desert .
If our two planes aren 't enough to cover areas the cars can 't reach
I 'll ask permission from the chief to hire a couple more .
Ben , get yourself something to eat and grab some sleep .
I don 't want you wearing yourself out so you 'll fold up on us .
- BEN : I 've a little score to settle . - CAPTAIN : We all have .
- Report from Washington , Captain . - All right , thanks .
Fingerprints on the trailer check out real good .
Mr. Elinson was an FBI agent on vacation with his wife and two children .
Call the local FBI office . They 've got a stake in this case , now .
Tell them Mr. Elinson 's vacation has been extended indefinitely .
GRAHAM : It 's nice to get off that desert .
- It must have been 110 out there today . - At least .
Captain Edwards
this is Robert Graham from the FBI office in Alamogordo .
- GRAHAM : How do you do ? - CAPTAIN : Sit down .
Ben here bring you up to date on this business ?
Yes , sir , we went over these exhibits before we left for the desert .
I took him to where we found the trailer and to Johnson 's store .
We 've been there all day . Nothing .
CAPTAIN : Any ideas , Mr. Graham ?
None that make any sense .
I thought you FBI guys were all Quiz Kids , solved everything right away .
I did , too , when I applied for the job .
The planes and cars haven 't found anything .
Give them time . People don 't just drop off the face of the Earth without a trace .
We 'll find them .
You know what that is ?
It beats me . Has it been identified yet ?
No , an officer took it to a friend who teaches zoology at the college .
He said he 'd never seen anything like it .
Lots of evidence , loaded with clues , but nothing adds up .
The Elinson girl is our only real bet . Any news on her ?
No change . I checked with the hospital a half-hour ago .
I 'd like to send this to our Washington bureau .
They might be able to identify it .
Or prove that it 's nothing .
All right with me .
( Knocking )
CAPTAIN : Come in .
- Hello , Fred . Glad to see you , Ben . - Hi , Doc , how are you ?
You two know each other ?
I don 't believe so .
Dr. Putnam , County Medical Officer . Robert Graham .
- He 's with the FBI . Watch your language . - I will .
DOC : I finished the autopsy on Gramps . You want it technical or plain ?
Just plain , Doc . Get to the verb .
Old man Johnson could have died in any one of five ways :
His neck and back were broken , his chest crushed , his skull fractured
and here 's one for Sherlock Holmes :
There was enough formic acid in him to kill 20 men .
( Dramatic instrumental climax )
I still don 't get this .
Doctors Medford , two of them . Department of Agriculture .
You sent that cast to your outfit in Washington , didn 't you ?
Yeah .
Does this mean that somebody has identified it ?
I don 't know .
- BEN : Great . - AIRMAN : Pardon me , sir .
The plane has landed . It 'll load over there .
Thanks .
- GRAHAM : Got a match ? - BEN : Yeah .
( Roaring of plane engine )
Okay , thank you .
GRAHAM : Dr. Medford ?
Are you Dr. Medford ?
Yes , yes . No need to shout .
You 're the people . They said you 'd meet us .
BEN : That 's right .
I 'm Bob Graham .
- How do you do ? - This is Sgt. Ben Peterson .
- You 're the one who found the print ? - Yeah , that 's right .
Pat , hurry up .
PAT : I 'm caught .
- OFFICER : Can I help ? - PAT : No , I can manage it .
This is the other Dr. Medford , my daughter , Patricia .
This is the man who found the print . Sergeant ...
- Ben Peterson . - How do you do ?
Then you must be Mr. Robert Graham .
- Yes , how do you do ? - Hello .
We 've got a car to take you to the hotel .
That can wait . We have work to do .
I want to read all your reports right away . Come on , Pat .
PAT : Excuse me , sir .
I should have had this suit pressed .
She 's quite a doctor .
If she takes care of sick people , I think I 'll get a fever real quick .
GRAHAM : This is where the car and trailer were found .
Twelve miles down this road is the Johnson store .
Thank you .
Why did the FBI send that print to the Department of Agriculture ?
They weren 't able to identify it .
- PAT : You only found one print ? - BEN : That 's right , miss .
Have you identified it ?
The Medical Officer 's report on Johnson suggests we were certainly wrong
to even consider this might be a hoax . Read that , Doctor .
Tell me
in what area was the atomic bomb exploded , the first one , back in 1945 ?
Right here in this same general area . White Sands .
1945 . That 's nine years ago .
Genetically , it 's certainly possible .
We 're grown up . There 's no need to play footsie with us . We resent it .
If you know what this thing is , Doctor , I suggest you tell us .
We 're assigned to this case , too .
Mr. Graham , we cannot tell you until we 're certain of our theory .
I 'd like to first stop off at the drug store and then see the Elinson girl .
She 's still in shock , Doctor . She hasn 't talked yet .
After the girl , I want to examine the territory where you found the print .
You were saying ?
As I explained to Mrs. Johnson , the little girl 's aunt
we hesitate in using a curare to diminish the spasms . She 's too young .
Narcosynthesis would be useless until we overcome the aphonia .
- What 's aphonia ? - Loss of voice .
PSYCHIATRIST : She 's a classic case of hysteria conversion .
Only a severe catharsis could jolt her at all .
DR. MEDFORD : May I have a small glass ?
- PSYCHIATRIST : Yes , certainly . - DR . MEDFORD : Pat , that acid we got ...
Acid ?
DR. MEDFORD : Formic , Doctor . Thank you .
It may provide the jolt you need .
Them !
( Dramatic instrumental music )
May we visit the desert now ?
It 's getting late .
It 's later than you think .
( Dramatic instrumental music )
Thank you .
Quite a breeze .
- The goggles , Doctor . - What about them ?
You 're supposed to wear them over your eyes .
Oh , thank you .
Yes , that is better .
- So this is where the car and trailer were ? - Yes , sir . Excuse me .
- Yes , thank you . - The print was found right over there .
BEN : We found it here , by the fire .
You see , there 's nothing there now .
Has there been any report of a strange mound ?
A cone-shaped structure ? Something recently formed ?
No , sir .
Sergeant , would you mind if we looked around a little more ?
Anything you say , Doctor .
Rather slim pickings for food , Dad .
They 'd turn carnivorous for lack of a habitual diet .
I believe you 're right .
What would turn carnivorous ?
- PAT : My father will tell you . - GRAHAM : When ?
- When he 's positive . - Now , look , miss ...
Doctor ... .
If the " Doctor " bothers you , why don 't you call me " Pat . "
I 'd like to .
I 've got a job to do , and enough mystery on my hands
without that old ...
I mean , your father complicating things .
He is one of the world 's greatest myrmecologists .
Myrmecologists ! You see , that 's what I mean !
Why don 't we all talk English ? Then we 'd have some understanding .
DR. MEDFORD : Pat !
Come here .
It 's the same kind of print . Look at it , Doctor .
It 's gigantic .
Over 12 centimeters .
That would make the entire- -
About two and a half meters in length . Over 8 feet .
See if there are more .
- This is monstrous . - So is the murder of five people , Doctor .
The direction of that print would indicate it came from that way .
Perhaps we should visit the store . There may be more there now .
Look here , before we do any more visiting , I want to know exactly what this " it " is .
Gentlemen , I understand your impatience .
I know you are concerned with solving what is essentially a local crime
but please believe me , I am not being coy with you .
If I 'm wrong , no harm has been done . But if I 'm correct
and the mounting evidence only fortifies my theory
then something incredible has happened in this desert .
In which case , none of us will dare risk revealing it , because
none of us can risk a nationwide panic .
A Panic ?
( High-pitched stridulation )
( Gunshots )
Get the antennae ! Get the antennae !
Get the other antenna !
Get the other antenna ! He 's helpless without them !
( High-pitched stridulation stops )
BEN : What is it ?
Spades appears to be Camponotus vicinus .
Of the family of Formicidae . An ant .
An ant ? I don 't believe it . It 's not possible !
Then this is what got Ed Blackburn , Gramps Johnson , and the rest ?
Yes . A fantastic mutation .
Probably caused by lingering radiation from the first atomic bomb .
Notice its odor ?
Formic acid ? That 's why the girl reacted so violently .
The Coroner said that Gramps was filled with it .
DR. MEDFORD : See that ? It 's the stinger .
Ants use their mandibles to rend , tear and hold their victims
but they kill with that , by injecting formic acid .
Mr. Johnson was stung to death .
There 's no time to lose . We must find the colony , the nest .
There 's more of them ?
This was probably just a scout , foraging for food .
You heard the sound . The stridulation .
It communicated with others in the colony .
You mean these things send messages ?
Of course . All insects have means of communication with their own kind !
( High-pitched stridulation recommences )
We may be witnesses to a Biblical prophesy come true .
" And there shall be destruction and darkness come upon creation .
" And the Beasts shall reign over the earth . "
( High-pitched stridulation continues )
Doctor , this nest we 're looking for . How many giant ants will be in it ?
General , I really don 't know .
If they follow the usual pattern of their species , the nest
depending upon its age , may contain hundreds or thousands .
- Thousands , Doctor ? - It 's possible .
Look , if we run into thousands of the thing you killed yesterday
it 'll take a bomber squadron plus an infantry regiment to mop up .
How could we keep that a secret ?
You 're jumping to conclusions , General .
There may not be nearly so many of these creatures as you suppose .
I 'm not supposing anything after looking at that carcass .
What I can 't understand is why no one has seen them until now .
For one reason , I don 't believe these creatures developed until recently .
For another , their being here
in these hundreds of thousands of square miles of desert is ...
No , that isn 't it .
- Could I speak to my daughter , please ? - Of course .
Thank you .
Hello , Pat ?
- DR. MEDFORD : Pat ? You there ? - BEN : That 's not the way to call .
BEN : We 're Search Able , call Search Baker .
- Right , General ? - Right .
Search Able to Search Baker .
Say , " Over . "
Then say , " Over . "
Over !
Medford and Baker to Medford and Able . Go ahead , Dad . Over .
Have you found anything yet ?
Say , " Over . "
- I just said it . - I know . Say it again .
Over !
Baker to Able : Not yet .
We 're about three quarters of the way across our sector .
We 're now at coordinates : Charlie-6 . Over .
DR. MEDFORD : Don 't pass up a thing .
Let me know when you find anything .
If you 're finished say , " Over and out . "
- She knows I 'm through talking . - I know she does .
It 's a rule . You 've got to say it . Right , General ?
- GENERAL : Right . - DR . MEDFORD : Ridiculous .
- Lot of good your rules will do- - - Over and out .
Now you 're happy -
( Exasperated sigh )
Real calm fellow , isn 't he ?
Worried about him ?
A little . He 's not a young man . He shouldn 't have made this trip , but
he 's a scientist and this is a scientist 's dream come true .
( Suspenseful instrumental music )
PAT : Hold it !
PAT : Fly back over it and get as close as you can .
( High-pitched stridulation )
You 've just found your missing persons .
Look , Dr. Medford
you 're being inconsistent . First , you insist it 's top secret .
Nobody else must know or do anything about getting rid of these big ants .
DR. MEDFORD : Correct . Absolute secrecy is imperative .
But then you turn around and say that time is the most important thing .
I 've been told to take orders from you and give you what you ask for .
But if time is that important , why not let me go in tonight with some bombers
and wipe out that nest ?
If you 'll just calm down , General , I 'll explain .
DR. MEDFORD : Doctor , please put up that chart .
Time is important , more so than you realize .
But bombing that nest tonight would only aggravate our problem .
The reason none of them have been seen during the day
even by the police spotting planes
is because they hate the heat of the desert .
They forage between sunset and dawn , when it 's cool .
So half the colony wouldn 't even be inside the nest tonight .
Our best chance will be during the hottest part of the day tomorrow .
DR. MEDFORD : This illustrates a typical ant nest .
Observe the details .
Here is the entrance .
These are tunnels , corridors , and food chambers .
Note the wonderful and intricate engineering .
Water traps , so that none will drown during rains .
This is somewhat oversimplified , I admit
but it will give you an idea of what we are up against .
Do you know that some species of desert ants dig down
as deep as 30 feet or more ?
That nest we found today might go down hundreds of feet .
We can pinpoint that opening . Seal it up for good .
The creatures would only tunnel out somewhere else .
We don 't want that nest damaged . Not yet .
GRAHAM : What do we do ?
First , we wait until noon tomorrow .
By that time , all of them should be within the nest .
To keep them confined in there is our next problem .
We have two possibilities :
First would be to flood the nest .
Ants will not come through deep water . They breathe through their sides .
Excuse me , Doctor , there 's no water line within 20 miles of that place .
GENERAL : That 's why you asked about our meteorological station .
Any chance of getting cloud formations ?
Nothing that would make cloud seeding pay off .
Nobody 's had any luck in making rain in this part of the desert .
The second possibility ?
Enough heat to drive the ants deeper down into the nest , and hold them down .
But no bombing ?
What about phosphorus ? We can lay it over that mound with bazookas .
That would keep the surface area hot .
What happens after that ?
We then drop cyanide gas into the opening and kill them .
How can you be sure you 'll get all of them ?
We go down into the nest and find out .
( Suspenseful instrumental music )
( Dramatic instrumental music )
Don 't forget to tap me when you get that wired , General .
Don 't rush me . I 'm doing this by the book .
It 's the first time I ever loaded one of these babies .
That makes us even . This is the first time I 've ever given orders to a general .
( Suspenseful instrumental music )
We should 've waited for it to cool more .
We don 't dare lose time getting cyanide into that nest .
( High-pitched stridulation )
( Explosions )
DR. MEDFORD : Marvelously made .
Marvelous . Tell me , you only saw the one live ant ?
He seemed to be trying to get out , rather than get us .
He stopped moving when the gas hit him . Then he dropped out of sight .
Didn 't see or hear a thing from then on .
BEN : You think they 're all dead ?
I think so . You used enough gas .
All parts of the nest should have been thoroughly saturated by now .
If I can still raise an arm when we get out of here
I 'll show you how well saturated I can get .
BEN : I 'm with you .
DR. MEDFORD : If I were younger , I ...
GRAHAM : What are you made up for ?
I 'm going with you and Ben .
No , you 're not .
PAT : Someone with scientific knowledge has to go .
My father is physically unable to do it . That leaves me .
That leaves you here . We don 't know what we 'll find down there .
One thing for sure , it 's no place for you or any other woman .
DR. MEDFORD : She wanted to go , Robert . As a scientist , I couldn 't forbid her .
- PAT : A trained observer has to go . - GRAHAM : What for ?
There are more important things than finding dead ants .
- You wouldn 't know what to look for ! - You tell us what .
There 's no time to give you a course in insect pathology !
So let 's stop talking and get on with it .
Okay .
PAT : Don 't worry , Dad .
GRAHAM : Good luck , Sergeant .
GRAHAM : You come last , Pat .
Throw us the rest of the stuff down when I signal .
( Suspenseful instrumental music )
PAT : Hold it .
PAT : They 're dead or they would have attacked us right away .
( Suspenseful instrumental music )
PAT : Look . Held together with saliva .
BEN : Spit is all that 's holding me together right now , too .
( Scraping )
( High-pitched stridulation )
( Stridulation stops )
GRAHAM : How come the gas didn 't kill them ?
PAT : The chamber looked caved in from the bombing .
PAT : Sealed up that way , the gas couldn 't reach them .
GRAHAM : If we run into any more live ones , we 're getting out of here .
( Suspenseful instrumental music )
PAT : This is it !
The queen 's chamber , and the eggs .
- PAT : This is what I was afraid of . - GRAHAM : What 's wrong ?
PAT : They 're empty .
- GRAHAM : What came out is dead , right ? - PAT : Not the ones hatched from these !
PAT : Now destroy everything in here . Burn it !
- GRAHAM : What ? - PAT : I said burn it . Burn everything !
( Dramatic instrumental music )
Very strange .
DR. MEDFORD : Most unusual .
PAT : No larvae or pupae in the egg chamber .
PAT : They seemed to hatch directly from the eggs .
PAT : I attribute it to the mutation process .
That 's the logical conclusion .
You feel sure those two have gone ? You found no winged ants ?
PAT : We saw only worker ants .
I don 't get it . You act like it was the end of the world .
It could be .
These two empty egg cases contained queen ants .
Newborn queen ants have wings , so have their consorts , male ants .
- You found no ants with wings ? - Not a one .
The fact is we didn 't destroy this first nest soon enough !
Two young queen ants hatched out , dried their wings and flew away
each with one or more winged males . They 've gone on their wedding flight .
We needn 't worry about the males . They 'll die very quickly , but the queens- -
Doctor , are you telling us there 'll be other nests ?
A single queen can lay thousands of eggs .
From these will hatch dozens of other queens , who may in turn ...
GENERAL : How far can they fly ?
These giants ? I don 't know .
Ordinary queens of the smaller species have very limited flying powers .
They 're dependent mostly on winds and thermal currents to carry them along .
They have been found in the stratosphere . But these giants ...
I don 't know , you guess .
I thought today was the end of them .
No .
We haven 't seen the end of them .
We 've only had a view of the beginning of what may be the end of us .
We 'd better inform Washington , General .
( Dramatic instrumental music )
( indistinct chatter )
OFFICIAL : Sergeant Peterson .
- Sir ? - What about your superiors ?
Do they know these creatures are causing the crimes in your desert ?
No , sir , they don 't .
Gen. O 'Brien and Dr. Medford felt that absolute secrecy
about the existence of the big ants was essential .
Do you also think this extraordinary hush-hush is necessary ?
Yes . I don 't think there 's a police force anywhere that could handle the panic
if people found out these babies were loose .
Gentlemen , I believe we are ready .
Some of you have displayed incredulous attitudes towards our reports and photos .
The rest of you are trying to understand the gravity of our situation
but repeatedly ask how really serious it is .
For your edification , I have prepared a short film
which I hope will give you some idea of the nature of the creatures we face .
In a small way , of course .
Robert , please turn out the lights .
DR. MEDFORD : These ants and related species are common to most of America .
In fact , you can find them in backyards , empty lots , and fields
throughout the temperate zones of the world .
They haven 't changed in form or habits
for more than 50 million years .
Here , for instance , is one such specimen
that got himself trapped in amber , which we know is at least that old .
Now we come to some different kind of ants .
The big fellow there , feeding on the smaller , red grease-eaters
is of a savage species called Camponotus vicinus Mayr .
He 's of a desert variety .
Very similar to the giant mutations we found in New Mexico .
There is a side view of a small nest .
Those white objects are ant eggs .
Ants don 't see well at all .
They hear , smell and locate objects with their radar-like antennae .
Only after food or an enemy is located with the antennae
are the savage mandibles put to work .
Now , gentlemen , watch this demonstration of power .
A pebble has blocked the entrance to the nest .
That creature is determined to remove the obstacle .
Note how the mandibles are used to grasp the pebble and pull it aside
with only a slight assist from another ant .
There 's the same pebble on a laboratory scale .
Balancing it , is a dish containing 20 ants .
We 've learned that one of these quarter-inch long insects can lift
20 times its own weight .
That 's equal to one of you lifting a ton and a half or more !
Here are rare shots of a newborn queen and her consorts .
Technically , she should be referred to as a princess , until after the mating flight .
Now there is a close shot of a winged male .
Males are unequipped for survival beyond the mating and die soon after .
The queen flies on , or more precisely , is borne by the winds
until her need prompts her to seek a place to lay eggs .
Does a queen ever fly away from her nest once she 's established it ?
No , never . She loses her wings after the wedding flight .
DR. MEDFORD : See ? One has dropped off .
Now she starts her function of establishing a place
in which to lay her eggs and begin the nest .
Queens live quite a long time . They continue to lay eggs
from the one mating
for from 15 to 17 years .
Here are ants at war .
As you can see , ants are savage , ruthless and courageous fighters .
This fight lasted 72 hours between those two alone .
Ants are the only creatures on Earth other than man
who make war .
They campaign . They are chronic aggressors .
They make slave laborers of the captives they don 't kill .
None of the ants previously seen by man were more than an inch in length .
Most were considerably under that size .
But even the most minute of them have an instinct and talent for industry
social organization and savagery
that makes man look feeble by comparison .
How large were the ants you found ?
DR. MEDFORD : The smallest measured nine feet in body length .
That , gentlemen , is why you are here .
To consider this problem .
And I hope , solve it . Because unless you solve it
unless these queens are located and destroyed
before they 've established thriving colonies and can produce
heaven alone knows how many more queen ants
man , as the dominant species of life on Earth
will probably be extinct
within a year , Doc ?
( sighs )
( Ominous instrumental music )
NEWSMAN : How about some information , Senator ?
SENATOR : Sorry , no comment .
There must be something you can tell us .
All the newswire services , AP , UP , INS , are in there , but nothing 's coming out .
No newsmen are being allowed in there .
What was that mysterious 3 : 00 a.m. meeting about ?
Can 't tell you a thing , boys , sorry .
There are about a million radio receivers installed in there , too .
- NEWSMAN 2 : Why ? - NEWSMAN : I don 't know .
Texans . When bigger stories are told , Texans will tell them .
Should fit in with the kind of stuff they 're looking for upstairs .
- Know what 's going on in this building ? - No .
Real " T.S. " stuff . Top Secret .
Okay , we 'll meet you at the airport in 20 minutes .
Says he can have us in Brownsville in less than three hours .
DR. MEDFORD : Good luck , Bob .
They ain 't kidding me . Nobody is . Not you , not anybody .
This isn 't a hospital . This is a loony bin . A nuthouse .
Do you think I 'm crazy ? I don 't care what you think . I 'm not !
I saw those things with my own two eyes !
Do you think anybody could make it up ? A guy would have to be nuts ...
You 're a flyer . You didn 't get that yard sitting on the ground .
You 've seen guys blow their stacks .
Do you think I act and talk like a guy who has lost his marbles ?
Tell us what you saw , Mr. Crotty .
I 've told those head-shrinking doctors four dozen times ! I 'm sick of it .
I tell them and I get laughed at and clucked over .
You promise not to laugh at me ?
Promise .
Okay .
I was flying south from Corpus Christi , heading here , Brownsville .
I turned in from the Gulf , heading for the airport about 20 miles out
all of a sudden I see these flying saucers .
Three of them . One big and two little ones .
I had to do some fancy flying or they 'd have run right into me .
I dived down and landed in the first place I saw , a street .
I 've never been so rattled in my life .
I cracked up a little , sure .
I plowed into an old Ford and ended up on someone 's porch .
Who wouldn 't lose their head after seeing something like that ?
- They were flying saucers ? - I don 't know what else to call them .
CROTTY : They were shaped
like ants .
It sounds crazy but that 's what they were shaped like .
The big one was about 15 feet long and had wings like a fly .
The other two seemed to be chasing the big one . One here . Two here .
They zoomed around me like kamikazes . Scared me out of my pants !
Excuse me , ma 'am .
They said that Ford wasn 't a new one . It was all beat up to begin with .
So what 's all the beef ?
You don 't believe me either . Do you ?
On the contrary , we do .
You do ?
Good .
What direction were these flying saucers going the last time you saw them ?
West , I 'd say . Yes , due west .
Will you get me out of here ?
- We 'll speak to the doctor about it . - I 'd appreciate it .
Try and get my clothes , too . They only gave me these slippers
but not even a rope to hold up my pants .
- We 'll be seeing you . - Be right neighborly if you could help .
I 'll sure be hoping .
- DOCTOR : Mr. Graham ? - GRAHAM : Yes ?
How was your talk with Mr. Crotty ?
You 're wise to keep him locked up , Doctor .
I 've recommended his release . He 's not demented .
I 'm convinced he 's trying to pull a publicity stunt with this weird story .
The government wants him to be kept here
so he doesn 't get any publicity .
The government ?
He 's to have no visitors .
If any information is given out about him , you 'll be held responsible .
GRAHAM : I can 't tell you why this is essential .
We 'll let you know as soon as possible . We 'll tell you when he 's well .
A bit more than 700 air miles from White Sands to Brownsville .
Southeast .
This Crotty said they were heading west when he saw them .
I believe him .
There were strong easterly winds the day Crotty saw the ants .
They 'd follow the line of least resistance .
We can surmise that one of the queens , possibly both of them
can create nests in this general area .
We 'd better inform the Mexican authorities
and concentrate our search efforts here .
As far south as Panama . As far north as
Santa Barbara , on the California coast .
That 's an awful lot of area .
( Telephone rings )
I 'll get it .
Hello ?
Dr. Medford speaking .
What ?
I 'll be right there .
( Dramatic instrumental music )
" A nest hatched aboard a ship at sea . "
( Dramatic instrumental music swells )
( Beeping in Morse code )
( Gunshots )
( Screaming )
( High-pitched stridulation )
ADMIRAL : I 'm sure you 'll be interested in this report I just received :
" U.S.S. Milwaukee got radio bearing on S.S. Viking before signal stopped .
" Milwaukee proceeded at once to location .
" Two seamen from Viking rescued from sea by Milwaukee .
" Seamen said no survivors remained aboard Viking .
" Not possible to put aboard search and rescue party ...
" ... as Viking was infested with the giant ants . "
Upon my orders , the 8.8 . Viking has been sunk with naval gunfire .
This was accomplished at 0700 this morning .
I don 't see how a ship at sea could ...
1st OFFICIAL : Dr. Medford
how could these giant creatures get aboard that vessel unseen ?
The S.S. Viking anchored in Acapulco , Mexico , for three days and four nights .
It 's then and there we believe one of these missing queen ants flew aboard .
Please give them your information .
" Owners of the 8.8 . Viking reported that on hold number one ...
" ... the hatch cover was off during the entire time of loading . Even at night .
" The crew had shore leave every night so only a skeleton crew remained on watch . "
It was quite possible for a queen ant to have flown onto that ship unseen .
An open hold would be inviting as a place to lay her eggs and hatch out a nest .
I think it 's time to inform the public . It can 't be kept a secret indefinitely .
We can 't risk it , sir .
But you already have .
The entire crew of the cruiser Milwaukee knows about these things now .
They know , but the Milwaukee will be kept at sea until this is resolved .
What do those flags on the map indicate ?
These four indicate where we found dead male ants .
The most recent finding was about four days ago near Mt . Wilson in California .
It was decomposed and must have been there for a month to five weeks .
This flag , at Los Angeles , indicates a lead .
Mr. Graham and Sgt. Ben Peterson are there now .
They were flown there by Maj. Kibbee to check on a large sugar theft .
Forty tons , to be exact .
( Train whistle blows )
GRAHAM : When was this car broken into ?
I told you , Friday night .
Yard watchman claims he didn 't see or hear a thing .
What 's so important you got to work on Sunday ?
Where 's the watchman ?
City jail . Any boob knows you need trucks to carry away 40 tons of stuff .
Said he didn 't hear them . He 's either lying or he 's deaf .
And he ain 't deaf .
- GRAHAM : Let 's go see him . - BEN : Yeah .
Thanks , buddy .
After spoiling my day off you could at least tell me
how come a government cop is so interested in this deal .
He 's got a sweet tooth .
GRAHAM : It 's the only job you 've ever had ?
I 've had a clean record for 30 years at the railroad .
Yard cop thinks you made a deal not to see that car broken into .
What sense does that make ?
Is sugar rare cargo ? ls there a black market for it ?
Did you ever hear of a fence for hot sugar ?
If I made a deal with crooks , it wouldn 't be for 40 tons of sugar !
I swear I didn 't hear a thing Friday night .
BEN : I 'll be right back .
( Woman crying )
That woman just identified the body of her husband . See him right away .
WATCHMAN : I 've never had anything to do with crooks . I 'm an honest man .
Sure , you can go home now . Take care of him , will you ?
Thank you .
I don 't think this happened in a machine .
Any machine that pulled hard enough to tear his arm off at the shoulder
would also have chopped up his face .
Look at the laceration across his chest .
Can 't figure it , except he died from shock and loss of blood .
Thanks very much .
His name 's Thomas Lodge .
Police found him , 6 : 30 a.m. His car jumped a curb , went into a sign
but not hard enough to do that . They couldn 't find the other arm .
His wife said that he left the house at 5 : 45 .
He had his two kids with him . No sign of the kids yet .
( Melancholic instrumental music )
GRAHAM : Mrs. Lodge
was your husband accustomed to taking his boys out so early ?
Tom works on Sunday from 9 : 00 to 7 : 00 . It 's an extra job he had .
He works so hard , he doesn 't have much time to spend with Jerry and Mike .
Sundays they get up early and go somewhere together to play .
Do you know where they might have gone this morning ?
Where ?
They go different places .
Last Sunday , Tom took the boys to the zoo .
They had such a good time .
Tom fixed it with a keeper so they could get in early
and watch the feeding of the animals .
Jerry talked about it all week .
Where else did they go ?
Sometimes Tom took them boat riding at MacArthur Park .
For pony rides and miniature golf .
They always come home so happy . And so dirty !
I kept asking Tom to do things where they won 't get so dirty .
I spent the rest of the day cleaning them .
Can I see you a moment ?
- BEN : Rough ? - GRAHAM : Yeah .
BEN : Bob , these are the two officers who found Lodge .
- This is Ryan . - Sutton .
Patrolmen Sutton and Ryan . This is Bob Graham .
Dr. Medford and Pat are flying here with Gen. O 'Brien tonight .
Kibbee called . He 'll be over after he 's had a little breakfast .
Show me on the map just exactly where you found Lodge .
- Right there . - And he was dead when you found him ?
Where 's MacArthur Park ?
That 's a long ways .
GRAHAM : We 've got to find out where he took the kids .
He couldn 't have driven far . He was too cut up .
Is there any area where you found him where he might 've taken the kids
for a boat ride or miniature golf ? Pony rides , stuff like that .
RYAN : I don 't know any miniature golf courses .
Griffith Park is the closest where they rent horses .
That 's a long way , too . Doesn 't his wife know where they went ?
No .
Did you make any arrests this morning , say between 4 : 00 a.m. and noon ?
RYAN : Yes , sir .
Four . Three drunks and a traffic citation .
GRAHAM : I 'd like to talk to them .
They might have seen something that 'll help us .
Where were you going when you were arrested ?
I don 't know .
I don 't even know where I was coming from .
- How about you ? - I don 't know either .
As I said before , I prefer the informal type of social life .
- I disagree with you . - Really ?
I 'm at my best in my white tie and tails .
All right , Beau Brummell , knock it off .
Look , miss ...
- All I did was go through a red light . - At 60 mph ?
- Was something chasing you ? - No , I was in a hurry to get home .
Where from ?
I spent the night with a sick friend .
I 'd rather not mention any names , he 's married .
- Okay , you can go . - Thank you .
I 'm through with them . Let them go back to the tank and sleep it off .
- All right , let 's go . - With pleasure , sir .
GRAHAM : You said there were three ?
The other one 's in the alcoholic ward at the hospital .
Practically a permanent resident there .
GRAHAM : Let 's go talk to him , too .
Sneaked out of here Saturday afternoon . Back at 5 : 00 this morning .
You can talk to him , but I don 't think he 'll cooperate .
Hey , Admiral , are we gonna be drafted ?
No , sir .
DOCTOR : Behave yourself , Harry . This is the man . Mind your manners .
- If he gives you trouble , I 'm outside . - He won 't .
BEN : Hello , Jensen . How are you ?
How do , gentlemen ? Looking for recruits ?
KIBBEE : Not today .
- Jensen , you come here often , don 't you ? - I like it here .
- What have you been doing lately ? - Same as always , nothing .
But I got some deals on .
GRAHAM : Sure .
You didn 't see anything unusual yesterday or this morning , did you ?
No , nothing unusual . Same as always .
They 're gone now .
I saw some little airplanes this morning .
Didn 't seem big enough for them to get into .
Big enough for who ?
The ants .
I 'd like to get out of here , but I ain 't joining the Army to do it !
- You can 't make me , there 's laws ! - We know .
Jensen , what kind of ants did you see ?
Big ones .
Ain 't there now .
- Mostly at night I see them . - Where ?
General , I 'll make a deal with you :
If you make me a sergeant in charge of the booze , and I 'll enlist .
Make me a sergeant in charge of the booze !
- Exactly where do these ants show up ? - In the river .
In the river .
I saw it once when it had water in it .
Now , when was that ?
JENSEN : Let me see .
GRAHAM : In the river bed .
Those big openings in the sides are like sewer outlets .
Jensen , how long have you been seeing these things ?
A long time . How long have I been here ?
The doctor says he was first admitted five months ago .
Thanks , Mac .
Take me with you and I 'll enlist , I promise .
Make me a sergeant !
JENSEN : Give me the booze ! Make me a sergeant . Give me the booze !
Please , my nerves !
( Dramatic instrumental music )
Which way is the hospital , Ryan ?
RYAN : Right over there .
Ben , come here .
Pretty good model of a kid 's idea of an L-1 .
Get on the radio and contact Mrs. Lodge .
Find out if the kids ever owned a plane like that . Wait for a report .
RYAN : Right .
Here 's tire marks .
New tires . Lodge had new tires on his car , didn 't he ?
Yeah .
KIBBEE : Hey , Bob ! Ben !
( Dramatic instrumental surge )
BEN : It 's them all right .
( Suspenseful instrumental music )
I don 't smell formic acid , do you ?
No , but it could all fall right into place .
Lodge and his kids down here flying their model plane .
Suddenly , the ants attack .
Lodge fights to protect his kids .
Somehow , he breaks away , gets into his car , and drives off .
But what about the kids ?
Maybe they ran away .
No , we 'd have picked them up by now .
Unless they ran in here .
RYAN : Mr. Graham !
That model plane belonged to the Lodge kids .
The husband used to bring the boys down here to fly it .
Got to be the same plane , same color . And there 's no model plane at home .
Where do these things go ? I mean , how far do they go ?
Don 't know for sure , but there 's more than 700 miles of them under the city .
( Dramatic instrumental music )
( Excited chatter )
NEWSMAN : Why is the Army sending troops into L.A. ?
NEWSMAN 2 : And a Marine regiment ?
NEWSMAN 3 : Why a special press conference at 5 : 00 on a Sunday ?
- You 'll just have to wait . - Why all the VIPs from Washington ?
Has the cold war gotten hot ?
Gentlemen , come in now .
This is the most serious crisis this city has ever faced .
There 's no time for questions . Listen carefully
so you can report the facts to your newspapers .
This is Dr. Harold Medford of the Department of Agriculture .
Gen. O 'Brien , Air Force Intelligence .
Gen. James , Army Intelligence . The others you know .
- Ready , sir ? - One moment .
- ANNOUNCER : Set , Charlie ? - CHARLIE : You 're on .
We interrupt all radio and television programs indefinitely .
Keep your radio and television sets turned on . This is an emergency .
I repeat , this is an emergency !
" By direction of the President of the United States ...
" ... and the Governor of the State of California , and the Mayor ...
" ... the city of Los Angeles is ...
" ... in the interests of public safety , hereby under martial law .
( Exclamations of surprise )
" Curfew is at 1800 hours .
" Any persons on the street or outside their quarters after 6 : 00 p.m ...
" ... will be subject to arrest by military police . "
Now as for the reasons for this most drastic decision :
A couple of months ago in the New Mexico desert , giant ants were discovered .
They 're similar in appearance to the ones you 're familiar with .
Except they are mutations , ranging in size from 9 to 12 feet in length .
The New Mexico colony was destroyed , but two queen ants escaped .
One has been found and destroyed . The other has not yet been found .
It has established a nest in the storm drains beneath the streets of Los Angeles .
It 's not known how long this nest has been established
or how many of these lethal monsters have hatched .
Maybe a few , maybe thousands .
If new queen ants have hatched and escaped this nest
other American cities may be in danger .
These creatures are extremely dangerous .
They 've already killed a number of persons .
Stay in your homes . I repeat , stay in your homes !
Your personal safety , the safety of the entire city
depends upon your full cooperation with the military authorities .
( Dramatic instrumental music )
You got a pass to be down here , lady ?
- No , but I 'm with Mrs. Lodge . - This is a restricted area . Let 's go .
Hold it , Sergeant !
- This is the mother- - - They have no pass- -
Go talk to the general .
BEN : Good evening , Mrs. Lodge .
- Is there any word yet ? - No , not yet .
We 've got an awful lot of people to help find them .
- This may take awhile . Why not go home ? - Oh , no .
- I want to be here when- - - Sure . Take it easy and try not to worry .
ENGINEER : Since time is of the essence
I recommend we pour gasoline into those drains and light it .
It 'll burn out anything in there and we can still control the fire
so there 'll be no property damage on the street .
Any ants that get through , the troops can take care of .
We can 't do that until we know whether those two kids are in there .
Think there 's a chance they 're still alive ?
Are we supposed to jeopardize the lives of everyone for children
who in all probability are already dead ?
- Ask their mother that question . - She 's right over there .
I see what you mean .
We not only have her to think of , but as I told you before
we can 't risk fire until we know if any new queens have hatched
and flown out of this nest . Where 's Gen. O 'Brien ?
- He 's over there by the command car . - Thank you .
- Can we start now , General ? - I think so .
- How about it , Major ? - Waiting for more coverage to the north .
Contact the northern units , soldier .
- Northern units come in . - How about the south ?
All drains as far as Long Beach
are covered by bazookas or flamethrowers .
- Openings of these drains ? - Police and Marines are covering .
How about it , soldier ?
SOLDIER : Can 't contact northern units , sir .
GENERAL : Let 's go ahead anyway .
Gen. O 'Brien to all search units : Proceed into storm drains !
- O 'CONNELL : Yes , sir ? - GENERAL : Get moving .
O 'CONNELL : Come on , boys , let 's get rolling !
Roll them out of here !
( Dramatic instrumental music )
Watch yourself , Bob .
Graham in drain 203 .
Graham in drain 203 . In six-tenths of a mile , nothing to report . Over .
Medford in drain 207 .
Medford in drain 207 . In half of a mile . Nothing to report , over .
Peterson in drain 223 .
Peterson in 223 , we 're in six-tenths of a mile . Nothing to report , over .
KIBBEE : This is Kibbee in drain 192 .
Repeat , Kibbee in 192 , in eight-tenths . Nothing to report , over .
( Rumbling )
Wait a minute , hold it .
Kill the motor .
( Creaking )
- Did you hear that ? - Yeah .
This is Peterson ! Stop all motors !
( Strange tapping in pipes )
This is Peterson in drain 223 .
Peterson in drain 223 . We 're in just over a mile . I hear something .
( Tapping in pipes )
There it is again . Stand by .
Where does this thing go ?
DRIVER : That pipe runs into a main line drain that isn 't finished yet .
Still in the construction stage .
BEN : Give me a hand .
Tell them where I 'm going .
Peterson is going through the connecting feeder to drain 267 .
We 've heard what may be the kids . Repeat , we 've heard what may be the kids .
Stand by .
- BEN : There 's construction down there ? - DRIVER : Yeah .
- Tell O 'Brien to turn the work lights on . - Right .
My map shows a portion of drain 267 is unfinished
with construction postponed for the last 60 days .
If they 've left work lights installed , turn them on . Stand by .
( Banging )
Mike ? Jerry ? Are you there ?
- MIKE : Yes , we 're here ! - BEN : Schmitty , they 're alive !
They 're alive .
Tell Mrs. Lodge her boys are alive .
( High-pitched stridulation )
BEN : Mike , Jerry , stay where you are ! We 'll get you out , but don 't move !
BEN : There 's two ants in here .
I got a strong brood odor , like in the New Mexico nest !
Report that to O 'Brien . Tell him I must be near the nest .
I can 't use the flamethrower . The kids are right in the line of fire .
BEN : Tell O 'Brien to send in troops .
DRIVER : Peterson says it has the same smell as the nest in New Mexico .
" Brood odor , " he calls it . He asks for troops to be sent in .
He 's found the nest !
To all units , condition red . Drain 267 is the target area !
Repeat , condition red . Drain 267 is the target area !
( Message repeating on radios )
( Dramatic instrumental music )
Repeat , condition red . Drain 267 is the target area .
O 'Connors , bring up my jeep . I hope we 've found this nest in time .
( High-pitched stridulation )
BEN : Mike , Jerry , get in the corner !
BEN : Come on Jerry , Mike , let 's get out of here !
Come on , Mike .
We 're going through this pipe . There 's a man at the other end .
Keep crawling until you get down there . Understand ?
BEN : Grab hold . Go on .
BEN : Keep crawling , to the other end .
( High-pitched stridulation continues )
GRAHAM : Put your light over there !
Keep at them !
GRAHAM : Ben .
- How about the kids , Ben ? - They 're okay .
The pipe ...
Medics !
- Stop the firing ! - Cease fire !
No more explosives , we can 't risk closing off the nest .
Is there any type of gas we can use ?
We can 't take a chance , might poison the whole city .
We must locate the egg chamber , find out if any new queens have hatched .
( High-pitched stridulation stops )
Medics !
( Suspenseful instrumental music )
GENERAL : Start digging , you guys .
GENERAL : Hurry up , dig .
( High-pitched stridulation )
( High-pitched stridulation stops )
Hold it . Don 't burn anything until we get the okay .
- General , where 's Dr. Medford ? - He 's coming .
Is this it , Doctor ?
DR. MEDFORD : New princess ants . New queens .
This is the egg chamber . The same as we found in New Mexico .
GRAHAM : Are we too late ?
Fortunately , we 're in time .
I 'm certain no new queens have escaped from this nest .
The job will be done when these are destroyed .
Okay , burn them out .
Pat , if these monsters are a result of the first atomic bomb in 1945
what about all the others that have been exploded since then ?
I don 't know .
Nobody knows , Robert .
When man entered the atomic age , he opened a door into a new world .
What we 'll eventually find in that new world , nobody can predict .
( Dramatic instrumental climax )
( English SDH )